Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 8; 1p.; Russell, William, 1740-1818 (Box 5)
    Camp near Smith's - Just returned from Morristown, where Col. Abeel has been acquitted of the charge against him. Advises the publishing of certain letters in order to do some justice to Col. Abeel's character. Capt. Young wishes him to inform Gen. Greene that he has a horse which he wants to exchange for a Continental mare; describes them.
    ii, 28
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 7; 1p.; St. Clair, Arthur (Box 5)
    Crane's Mills - Requesting that a horse may be sent him, as his own is quite worn out and he has to make twenty or thirty miles daily. Has neither wax nor wafers to close his letters.
    ii, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 1; 1p.; Sandford, Lemuel and Five Selectmen of Reading (Box 5)
    Asking that Joseph Griffin, an artificer, may be discharged, as he has a large family in great need of assistance.
    ix, 108
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 20; 1p.; Sargent, Winthrop, 1753-1820 (Box 5)
    Gloucester - Desiring payment for his schooner, which was taken in April, 1779, on her passage from South Carolina. She was laden with rice, and was ordered to Samuel Allen Otis, Esq.
    ii, 29
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 19; 1p.; Sayles, D. (Box 5)
    Camp - Agreeable to the General's desire, has sent two orderly books for the use of Gen. Stark's brigade. Will report the teamsters to the General as soon as he gets their names.
    ii, 30
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1778 November 8; 1p.; Scammell, Alexander (Box 5)
    Two-horse wagon fully sufficient to haul wood, provisions, etc., and to transport those prisoners who may be shackled or unable to travel. If carelessness in the Provost-Marshal was the cause of the wagons being injured, will make him answerable for damaged. [Note.] Col. Scannell was killed September, 1781, at the siege of York.
    ii, 31
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 11; 1p.; Scammell, Alexander (Box 5)
    Desiring to know where the colliers are to be employed, and also where the horse-guard is kept, as he understands it hasn't been relieved for three months past. Suggests supplying a sentry from some other guard.
    ii, 32
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 May 8; 2pp.; Schuyler, Peter (Box 5)
    Albany - Acknowledging favor of 24th ult. Manner of court instituted at one time to try the offenses of enlisted bateauxmen and teamsters, and modes of punishment used. Discusses it's expediency in the present scarcity of hands.
    vii, 48
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 8; 2pp.; Schuyler, Peter (Box 5)
    Albany - Acknowledging his favor of the 4th inst. and promising to assist him in procuring boards; has taken measures which will certainly furnish between 12,000 and 15,000 by the 16th inst. Arrangements made for their transportation. Hopes to be of the party to New York.
    ii, 33
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 13; 1p.; Scott, Dr. (Box 5)
    Morris - Has found a mare, with the Continental brand, in the possession of Col. Berry that was stolen from him three years before. Desires the General's directions to Col. Berry on the premises.
    ii, 34
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 5; 1p.; Scull, P. (Box 5)
    War Office - Has been directed to furnish the enclosed list of articles which were ordered last April from France and are expected to arrive before the opening of the next campaign.
    ii, 38
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 20; 2pp.; Scull, P. (Box 5)
    War Office - Begging him to mark out some system by which Mr. Hiltziemer, the keeper of the public stables, may know who are and who are not entitled to have their horses kept at the public expense.
    ii, 39
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 21; 1p.; Scull, P. (Box 5)
    War Office - Enclosing an order on the assistant clothier at Fishkill to furnish Gen. Greene's department.
    v, 46
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 22; 1p.; Shaw, S. (Box 5)
    Quarters of the Artillery, Pluckemin - Concerning a horse left by Col. Harrison in the care of Capt. Pryor. By order of Gen. Knox, a ration was issued for said horse up to within a few days past, when the foragemaster refused to issue any more. As the case stands, Capt. Pryor must either turn the horse adrift or be at very great expense in keeping him till Col. Harrison's return.
    ii, 35
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 December 4; 1p.; Shaw, Thomas, 1753-1838 (Box 5)
    New London - Concerning a box of stationery shipped to His Excellency, Gen. Washington, and which he never received. Promising to look it up and have it sent on.
    ii, 40
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 October 30; 2pp.; Sheppard, William (Box 5)
    Providence - Complaining of the conduct of Mr. Charles Wittelsey, who tried his best to make mischief in Col. Glover's brigade and succeeded in almost creating a mutiny. Thinks Mr. Whittelsey deserves to be turned out of the service.
    ii, 43
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 9; 2pp.; Sheriff, Cornelius (Box 5)
    Camp - Smith's Clove - Acknowledging favor of 3d inst. Recommending particular attention and great exertion in the mater of transporting stores. Resolution of Congress concerning the commission in the quartermaster's department. If he draws commission, must pay and subsist his assistant.
    vi, 36
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 July 12; 2pp.; Sheriff, Cornelius (Box 5)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of the 4th, with certain returns. States to what extent Col. Sheriff may command Mr. Bond. Clothing for bateaux men. Enemy has plundered New Haven and burned Fairfield; their ravages inhuman and barbarous; their abuse to women exceeds all description.
    x, 19
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 1; 2pp.; Sheriff, Cornelius (Box 5)
    Wyoming -- Just left the army twenty-seven miles above Tioga healthy and spirited after penetrating the most interior part of the Indian country, destroying their towns and produce and laying waste the whole of their settlements. Describes the country as the richest and most beautiful in the world. Desires to go home and see how his affairs are situated. His pay inadequate to his expenses. Considerable waste of quartermaster's stores since the commencement of the expedition, especially on long and rapid marches. Number of horses much lessened. Will send returns later.
    iii, 99
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 22; 1p.; Sheriff, Cornelius (Box 5)
    Easton - Acknowledging his favor of the 14th inst. Disposition to be made of the boats. Finds it necessary to go home, but will be at headquarters before the troops reach there. [Note on back of MSS: "Died prior to December 8, 1779. See Col. Johnson's letter."]
    ii, 42
  - to Robert Lettis Hooper, 1779 November 14, 16; 2pp.; Sheriff, Cornelius (Box 5)
    Pompton - Desired by Gen. Greene to request Col. Hooper to call Col. Bond to a settlement in the pack-horse department. REPLY: Easton - In the strict line of Col. Sheriff's duty, not of his, to call Col. Bond to a settlement; will report the matter to Gen. Greene.
    ix, 66, 66a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 7; 1p.; Sherman, John (Box 5)
    Camp - Asking him to grant Capt. Bull's request for a horse, saddle and bridle, as he is directed to take charge of the men discharged from the 1st Connecticut Brigade to Dansbury.
    ii, 41
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 December 31; 1p. (Box 5)
    An imperfect return of established hospitals.
    ii, 44
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 23; 2pp.; Shreve, Israel (Box 5)
    Elizabethtown - Has received tents, but has no sort of wagon or carriage in case the enemy should move that way; begs that they may be sent immediately. Expedition certainly on foot at New York in flatboats, with their main body somewhere. Lines very weak; only his regiment and about one hundred militia between Acquacanac and Woodbridge.
    v, 65
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 25; 1p.; Shreve, Israel (Box 5)
    Elizabethtown - Acknowledging favor of 24th inst. Will get the tents out of town by night. Will apply for wagons.
    vi, 11
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 26; 1p.; Shreve, Israel (Box 5)
    Elizabethtown - Thought best to send the tents three miles back of the above place. Sends all the intelligence he could collect.
    v, 71
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Shreve, Israel (Box 5)
    Scotch Plains - Arrived after a long march in pretty good health and spirits. Enemy quiet at New York. Admiral Arbuthnot sailed last Friday. Asks that, if possible, his regiment may occupy Burlington barracks when the army goes into winter-quarters. His family lives there, and also he could recruit his regiment there against the opening of the next campaign.
    ix, 109
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 1p.; Sickels, Thomas (Box 5)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging favor of 7th inst. The money he needed has gone on. Promises portmanteaus shall be forwarded. Will ascertain price of clothing. Wants omission rectified in his monthly return.
    vi, 63
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 1p.; Sickels, Thomas (Box 5)
    Albany - Reason for delay in sending returns. No paper fit for use at Albany; begs for a few reams of good paper.
    iii, 100
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 11; 2pp.; Sickels, Thomas (Box 5)
    Albany - Promising to send the accounts ordered for the inspection of the Board of War sometime in the following month. Represents the small amount of their pay, the depreciated state of paper currency and the heavy taxes, and asks to know what subsistence money will be allowed. Destitute of cash to buy forage, which every day becomes dearer.
    ii, 45
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 15; 1p.; Sickels, Thomas (Box 5)
    Albany - Enclosing return of stores for the last month. Express that went to Philadelphia for money returned without any. People grumbling much at being kept out of their money. Begging him to remind Col. Abeel of the scales, weights and sheet-iron he gave him a memorandum of.
    ii, 46
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 4; 1p.; Sizer, William (Box 5)
    West Point - Asking that Sergeant Pool, being a proper boat-builder, may go with him.
    iii, 101
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 17; 1p.; Sizer, William (Box 5)
    Fishkill - Men under his command building the boats work from daylight till dark, with only the necessary time for breakfast or dinner. They have petitioned in consequence for a larger allowance of provisions; suggests a full ration and a half during this exigency.
    iii, 102
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 2pp.; Smallwood, William, 1732-1792 (Box 5)
    Camp, Sandy Beach - Has sent two sergeants, one corporal and fourteen privates, who say they are shipwrights and sailmakers; asks that they may be returned to the brigade as soon as their work is performed. In former drafts has never had the men properly returned. Tried in vain to get hoes for the men; hopes they can be furnished with them.
    iii, 103
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 15; 2pp.; Smallwood, William, 1732-1792 (Box 5)
    Camp - Sandy Beach - Asking that Mr. Ramsey and Mr. Morrow, purser and surgeon's made under Capt. Nicholson, may have a light wagon and two horses to carry themselves, their own and the captain's baggage to the Continental frigate Trumbull, the ship being all ready to sail.
    iii, 104
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 9; 1p.; Smallwood, William, 1732-1792 (Box 5)
    Camp - Requesting him in the most earnest manner, to press Col. Sheriff to furnish an account of such articles as were received by him for the Continent, out of the prize brig Lymetry and, if possible, to appear in person in order to facilitate a settlement between the public and the captors.
    ii, 48
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 26; 1p.; Smallwood, William, 1732-1792 (Box 5)
    Annapolis - By a late act of the Legislature of Maryland, no person can act in the Quartermaster's, Commissary or Forage departments if concerned in trade or traffic not incidental to the duties of office; this will occasion the resignation of Mr. Calhoun. Recommends Mr. John Bullen as his successor.
    ii, 47
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 4; 2pp.; Smith, Elijah (Box 5)
    Glanstonbury, Conn. - Asking for payment for a horse, worth at the time of its impressment £25. Gives all the details concerning the matter.
    iii, 105
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 28; 1p.; Smith, Hugh (Box 5)
    The Eastern post not arriving in time, the Southern rider departed without the mail. Would be exceedingly obliged if the General would give an order for one of his express-riders to take charge of it to Philadelphia. Cannot find a man for money.
    ii, 52
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 August 1; 1p.; Smith, John W. (Box 5)
    Smith's Clove - Stateing damages sustained on his farm during an encampment there of Gen. Sinclair's division; asks to whom he must apply for payment.
    vi, 110
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 June 21; 2pp.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Acknowledging favor of 12th inst. Stores sent forward. Quantity of clothing forwarded to Gen. Knox at Fishkill. Has appointed Mr. Rice, of Brookfield, foragemaster for that post. Will make scows as soon as possible; boatmen engaged. The town has great objections to a Continental ferry. Places chosen for stores.
    x, 11
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 8; 2pp.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Acknowledging letters of 13th and 14th ult. Forwarded by Mr. Laurence his accounts to December 1. Has appointed Mr. Josiah Harvey to furnish teams for transporting provisions in upper part of State. Called upon to send to Albany 1500 barrels of beef and pork and 90 loads of rum, rice, etc. For these and other demands a large sum of money is needed. Impossible to engage wagoners at twenty-six and two-thirds dollars per month on account of the depreciation of the currency.
    ii, 49
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 25; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Has transmitted by Mr. Shelden his accounts and returns for month of December. Has also forwarded part of the tools and all the salt, with the greater part of the stores at Westfield.
    ii, 50
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 26; 3pp.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Concerning the building of the boats. Opposition to this measure by the Selectmen of the town.
    viii, 90
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 13; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Enclosing account and return for the month of January; expects to want $ 25,000 before the 2d of March for transporting various articles.
    iv, 90
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 9; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Acknowledging favors of 19th and 29th ult. The $ 54,000 sent was all due before it arrived. Number of tents forwarded and their destination.
    vii, 53
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 22; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Sends Mr. Able King for a supply of money to enable him to perform the services demanded. Tents forwarded to Fishkill; stores destined for Albany gone forward.
    v, 56
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 2pp.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging letters of 9th and 22d ult. and 9th inst. Unfortunate mistake in sending tents to Albany. Discovery made which will shorten the route to Fishkill thirty miles. Money lost by not having known it before. Sum of money on the way to Mr. Smith. Compliments him on his punctuality. Hopes the wine sent to His Excellency was cased, otherwise the carters would ruin the quality by adulteration.
    vi, 55
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    New Windsor - In receipt of alarming letter from Board of War, relative to the need of lead. Asking him to make every exertion to aid Col. Chase in getting the lead on from Boston to Springfield, otherwise the consequences may be dreadful. Barrack-master department now under charge of Quartermaster-general.
    vi, 108
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 July 22; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Enclosing an account of services performed for the troops of the Convention from 1st September to the time they left Massachusetts.
    viii, 89
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 9; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - His order of the 4th inst. to furnish teams, transports, etc., shall be punctually attended to. Stores ordered by Gen. Knox, about twenty loads in all, will proceed to Claverack in a few days; also fifteen loads of clothing. Enclosing accounts and returns for the month of September.
    iii, 106
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 18; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Acknowledging order of the 5th inst. All the clothing ready has gone to Claverack; also sent 1000 bushels of salt. Requests a supply of cash to pay for transportation of stores.
    iii, 107
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 8; 2pp.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Acknowledging favor of 21st ult. Has forwarded a number of stores for Col. Hay. Accounts and returns for October. On account of depreciation of money, officers employed by him cannot furnish themselves with clothing; desires to know if clothing may not be delivered to them at the same rate as others in the service.
    ix, 111
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 13; 1p.; Smith, William (Box 5)
    Springfield - Enclosing his accounts and returns for January, sent by Conductor Avery, who has under his care to Newburgh twelve loads of clothing.
    ii, 51
  - to Armorer, n.d.; 1p.; Smith, William S. (Box 5)
    Order to repair the bearer's musket.
    xii, 68
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 24; 1p.; Spycer, Samuel (Box 5)
    Harriston (?) - After much trouble has reached the above place; enumerates the horses he has left behind him on his journey.
    ii, 53
  - to George Olney, 1779 October 13; 1p.; Starr, Ezra (Box 6)
    Danbury - Agreeable to request, has sent to New Milford for the box of paper belonging to His Excellency and will forward the same to the care of Col. Hay.
    iii, 108
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 14; 2pp.; Starr, John (Box 6)
    Smith's Tavern - Has heard of a little dispute between Col. Hay and Mr. Starr, respecting the distance each should cart the provisions. Remonstrates with him for this narrow point of view, pointing out how injurious it is to he public interest. New York State heavily handicapped by the enemy on the sea-coast and the savages on the frontier.
    vi, 67
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 September 27; 1p.; Starr, John (Box 6)
    West Point - Thinking that doubtless his feeling were hurt at the complaint made by Mr. Merchant not long since, encloses copies of some of the letters which passed on that occasion, showing that he (Greene) did not neglect to do justice to Maj. Starr's reputation.
    iv, 35
  - to Charles Pettit, 1779 January 28; 3pp.; Steel, Archibald (Box 6)
    Pittsburgh - Acknowledging the amount of the last draft made by him. Account of the trouble between him and Gen. McIntosh. Acquitted by a general court-martial of every charge against him; notwithstanding which, the General still keeps him under arrest; if this continues, the post must fail for want of provisions. Recommending certain gentlemen as disinterested judges of his and Gen. McIntosh's conduct.
    iv, 92
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 20; 2pp.; Steel, Archibald (Box 6)
    Pittsburgh - Acknowledging favor of the 20th ult. Beyond doubt that he has fallen under Gen. McIntosh's displeasure, but flatters himself that he has maintained a good character with his countrymen in general. Acquitted of all charges by the Court. Aware that it is his duty to cultivate harmony with his commanding officer, but quite impossible to do so with Gen. McIntosh. Is preparing his accounts. Difficulties of his situation. Breach between him and Gen. McIntosh so great that it can never be healed.
    iv, 91
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 September 29; 2pp.; Steel, Archibald (Box 6)
    West Point - Taking him to task severely for not sending any returns, and for not carrying out punctually the orders of Col. Broadhead.
    iv, 31
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 30; 2pp.; Steel, Archibald (Box 6)
    Martinsburg - Acknowledging favor of 29th September. Returns of stores and persons. Complaints of wages. Intends to set out for Fort Pitt to procure stores. Col. Broadhead's demands strictly attended to. Distressed for want of money; drivers destitute of almost every kind of clothing. In daily expectation of money from Mr. Pettit.
    ix, 110
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 16; 2pp.; Steel, Archibald (Box 6)
    Martinsburg - Acknowledging favors of the 2d and 19th ult. Question of his accounts; when they will be ready. His line of conduct approved by the Board of War. Certain moneys obtained in exchange for certificates. Great need of cash.
    ii, 56
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 July 12; 2pp.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of 8th inst. and accepting the offer of his services. Recommends particular car in pasturing the horses, also an application to Col. Hooper for smiths. Must apply to a magistrate in case inhabitants refuse to deliver up and public property in their hands.
    x, 14
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    Newtown - Has forwarded all the provisions. Will strictly comply with every order. Thinks fifty horses can be collected out of the different pastures fit for service. Has engaged wintering for 100 horses some distance from any public road. Has raised some fine potatoes; hopes Gen. Greene will accept of some barrels.
    iii, 109
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 8; 1p.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    Newtown - Acknowledging letter of 3d inst. Has sent on all the salt and flour; will send also fifty or sixty horses. Col. Biddle approves of the plan of providing stabling for 100 horses during the winter.
    iii, 110
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 19; 1p.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    Newtown - Has been making all preparations possible for Gen. Sullivan's army. Will send on one load of potatoes, and if possible, Mrs. Stephens will procure a firkin of butter.
    iii, 111
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 10; 1p.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    Newtown - Sending saddle of venison by an express. Will send some vegetables. Impossible to get butter or salt.
    viii, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 14; 1p.; Stephens, William (Box 6)
    Newtown - Delay of teams caused by heavy snowfall. Some time the following morning sixty sleds will start for Newbourgh [Newburg].
    ii, 59
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 20; 1p.; Steuben, Friedrich von (Box 6)
    New Windsor - Asking him to find a good house for himself and family in the neighborhood of the army, and to acquaint the quartermaster at Morristown with his choice, that he may apply to him on his arrival.
    ii, 58
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 February 7; 1p.; Stewart, Charles (Box 6)
    Camp, Paramus - Sending various returns.
    iv, 93
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 15; 2pp.; Stewart, Charles (Box 6)
    Headquarters - Very unwell and fearful of a tedious attack of sickness. A temporary magazine at the landing necessary to supply the posts at Elizabethtown, Newark and Springfield, etc.; also the bridge over Raritan wants repairing.
    iv, 94
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 1p.; Stewart, Charles (Box 6)
    Kain's Quarters - Obliged through sickness to leave camp in an hour, on his way toward Kingwood, his former residence. Desires him to order and express to go to Philadelphia by way of Trenton, with the packets the bearer will give him.
    ii, 55
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 February 26; 1p.; Stewart, Charles (Box 6)